Guide to the Annette T. Rubinstein Papers TAM.167
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Annette T. Rubinstein Papers
1937-2007
1946-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rubinstein, Annette Teta, 1910-2007.
TAM.167
7.6 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, and 3 folders in a shared manuscript box
Annette T. (Teta) Rubinstein was a Marxist educator, editor, writer, literary critic, and political activist born in New York in 1910. Among her numerous endeavors, she briefly taught philosophy at New York University, was Vice-Chairman for New York in the American Labor Party, was a teacher, owner and principal of the Robert Lewis Stevenson School, served as the Executive Secretary of the Committee for the Care of Young Children in Wartime, and was professor of English and American Literature at the Beijing Foreign Studies University. The collection includes biographical materials, correspondence and documentation of her educational and political activities.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Annette T. Rubinstein, 1994; additonal materials were donated in 2001, 2002, and 2007. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1994.008, 1994.013, and NPA.2002.058.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series:
Series I: Biographical
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Freedom of Information Act Files
Series IV: Lecture Tours
Series V: Political Activities
Series VI: Writings
Series VII: Addendum
Series VIII: Photographs
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Annette T. (Teta) Rubinstein (1910-2007), Marxist educator, editor, writer, literary critic and political activist, was born to socialist parents in New York on April 12, 1910 in an apartment on the top floor of the Manhattan School, a private school founded by her father to educate underprivileged immigrants. She taught philosophy at New York University while she completed her graduate studies in philosophy at Columbia with her 1934 dissertation, Realistic Ethics.
Although often critical of the its positions, Rubinstein was a member of the Communist Party from the 1930s into the 1950s. She was active in the American Labor Party and later became its Vice-Chairman for New York. In 1934 she began a long relationship with the Robert Louis Stevenson School, first as a teacher and later as owner and principal until her forced resignation in 1952. From 1941-1946 Rubinstein served as the Executive Secretary of the Committee for the Care of Young Children in Wartime. In the late 1940s she also served as the President of the West Side Child Care Council.
In the Spring of 1949, following the sudden death of the congressman for New York's 20th Congressional District, the ALP selected Rubinstein as its candidate in the subsequent special election. Also in 1949, the Robert Louis Stevenson School opened a Veterans Division to take advantage of the educational provisions of the GI Bill of Rights. The Veteran's Administration and New York Board of Education apparently responded to her political affiliations by invoking a series of technicalities to stop reimbursing the school. In 1952 Rubinstein severed her connection to Stevenson School and testified before the U.S. Senate and the House of Representatives' Un-American Activities Committee.
Following her unsuccessful pursuit of publishing employment Rubinstein focused on writing. The Great Tradition in English Literature: From Shakespeare to Shaw(1953) concentrated on the relationship of political and social movements to major literary works. To commemorate the late Congressman Vito Marcantonio, for whom Rubinstein had served as an aide, she edited I Vote My Conscience: Debates, Speeches and Writings of Vito Marcantonio, 1935-1950(1956). Rubinstein also generated a continuous stream of book reviews, literary criticism and articles, and worked as an editor on the Marxist periodicals Mainstream and Science and Society.
In 1958 Rubinstein ran for Lt. Governor of New York on the the Independent Socialist Party line (a coalition of socialists, Communists and Trotskyists). In 1960 ATR was instrumental in the creation of the Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience which focused on the issues of class discrimination and racism in the schools and in the courts and published several ATR pamphlets, including Attica 1971-1975(1975), The Black Panther Party and the Case of the New York 21(n.d.), and Suicides in Prision: A Cry for Help on Rikers Island(n.d.). She also edited Schools against Children: The Case for Community Control(Monthly Review Press, 1970).
In the late 1950s and 1960's Rubinstein lectured across the United States, Canada and Eastern Europe, and held visiting appointments at several Eastern European universities, including Karl Marx University in Leipzig. She visited the People's Republic of China in 1972, and returned in 1982-83 and 1987-88 as a professor of English and American Literature at the Beijing Foreign Studies University. While in China she created the textbook American Literature, Root and Flower: Significant Poets, Novelists and Dramatists, 1775-1955(Beijing, Foreign Language Teaching and Research Press, 1988).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Tamiment Library's Oral History of the American Left Collection (Series I) contains three interviews with Annette Rubinstein (OH 002). Cedric Belfrage Papers (TAM 143)
Scope and Content Note
This collections contains the papers of Annette Rubinstein, the bulk of which are from 1937-2007. The majority of the collection is made up of correspondence, from domestic and foreign correspondents, and her writings on Marxism and literary subjects. Other materials in the collection relate to her lecture tours and political activities in the 1940s and 1950s. The collection contains correspondence, Freedom of Information Act Files, newsletters, flyers, lecture notes, articles, and other ephemera. The collection is rich in activities related to Marxist scholarship, and Communist Political activities from the 1950s-1990s.
Communism -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Autobiographies.; Lectures.; Government records; Communists -- United States.; Drafts (documents); Articles.; Correspondence.; Humboldt, Charles; Magdoff, Harry; Lawson, John Howard, 1894-1977.; Rubinstein, Annette Teta, 1910-2007.; Rubinstein, Jean.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Sobell, Helen; Sobell, Morton; Wilkerson, Yolanda.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Wilkerson, Doxey Alphonso, 1905-1993.; Aronson, James; Ward, Henry Frederick, 1873-1966.; Brecht Forum (New York, N.Y.); Uphaus, Willard E. (Willard Edwin), 1890-1983.; Belfrage, Cedric, 1904-1990.
- Series I: Biographical
  Scope and Content Note
  This small series includes an undated autobiographical fragment pertaining to her childhood and early professional and political endeavors, an interview transcript, resumes, and ephemera.
  - Autobiographical Fragment, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birthday Celebrations, 1984, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interview (ATR interviewed by Rebecca MacLean), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Resume - Karl Marx University Resume - New York Times, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resume - New York Times, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Schappes, Morris - 85th Birthday and Jewish Currents Anniversary Celebration Program (ATR gave "Stranger than Fiction" address), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  The correspondence runs from the end of WWII to the early 1990s, and contains letters from domestic and foreign correspondents.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries A: Domestic
  Subseries B: Foreign
  - Subseries A: Domestic
    This series contains letters from correspondents in the United States. Prominent domestic correspondents include: James Aronson and Cedric Belfrage ( National Guardian), W. E. B. DuBois, Charles Humboldt ( Mainstream), John Howard Lawson, Harry Magdoff, Pete Seeger, Morton and Helen Sobell, Willard Uphaus, Dr. Harry F. Ward, and Doxey and Yolanda Wilkerson.
    - A (alphabetical), 1949-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aronson, James, 1961-1979, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - B, 1947-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Belfrage, Cedric, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Buhle, Mary Jo and Paul, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - C, 1950-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Criticism, Requests for (Chronological), 1946-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - D, 1946-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Doctoral Students, Requests for Information, 1963-1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - DuBois, W. E. B. - Correspondence, General, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - DuBois, W. E. B. - Documentary, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - DuBois, W. E. B. - Film Project, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - E-G, 1951-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - H-I, 1955-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Humboldt, Charles, 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - J-L, 1949-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lawson, John Howard, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - M, 1950-1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Magdoff, Harry, 1961-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mainstream, 1947-1962, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - N, 1951-1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - New York Marxist School, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - O-P, 1955-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - R, 1949-1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - S, 1949-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Sobell Committee (Helen and Morton Sobell), 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - T, 1958-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Truman, President Harry S. - ATR Letter Concerning HUAC, Jun, 7, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - V, 1964-1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - W, 1955-1990 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Wald, Alan, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Ward, Harry F., 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Wilkerson, Doxey and Yolanda, 1949-1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - World Fellowship (Rev. Dryden Phelps and Willard Uphaus), 1952-1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Y-Z, 1948-1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Subseries B: Foreign
    The foreign correspondence is principally with educators and others in the People's Republic of China, the German Democratic Republic, other socialist countries and Western Europe, and with her mother, Jean Rubinstein.
    - China Adler, Pat and Sol, 1984-1993 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - China: American Literature, Root and Flower 1775-1955(Publication of), American Women Writers Tour, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - China: C, 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - China: Crook, David and Isabel, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - China: D-K, 1982-1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - China: L, 1982-1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - China: Lii, Hui - U.S. Immigration Affidavit of Support (by ATR), 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - China: Marks, Marcia, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - China: P-W, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - China: X-Z, 1982-1994 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Czechoslovakia: A-L, 1958-1991 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Czechoslovakia: M-Z, 1960-1981 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Europe: Correspondence with Mother, Other Relatives (Chronological), 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Europe: Correspondence with Mother, Other Relatives (Chronological), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Europe, Eastern (Poland, USSR), 1954-1985 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Europe, Western (England, France, Sweden, etc.), 1958-1990 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - German Democratic Republic: A-F, 1960-1990 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - German Democratic Republic: G-L [1 of 2], 1959-1994 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - German Democratic Republic: G-L [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - German Democratic Republic: M-S, 1960-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - German Democratic Republic: T-Z, 1960-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Hungary, 1961-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III: Freedom of Information Act Files
  This series contains six 'books' of FBI files, arranged by book number, and Rubinstein's correspondence with the CIA and FBI.
  - Central Intelligence Agency: FOIA and Privacy Act Requests for Information, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation: FOIA Requests for Information, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - FOIA: Book I, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - FOIA: Book IA - Financial Investigation, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - FOIA: Book II, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - FOIA: Book III, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - FOIA: Book IV, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - FOIA: Book V, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Lecture Tours
  This series contains correspondence, flyers, itineraries, lecture notes and other teaching materials and provides a detailed account of her tours and travels.
  - Canada, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Canada, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Canada, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Canada, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Canada, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Canada, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - China: Cartoons, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - China: Diary, Dec 1972-Jan 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - China: Scrapbook, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - China: Teaching Material and Tour Itinerary, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Germany: Itinerary, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Germany: Lectures, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures, 1937-1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (California - Iowa), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Maryland - Wisconsin), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (California and Colorado), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Illinois - New York), 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Ohio - Wisconsin), 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Arizona - Colorado), 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Idaho - Wisconsin), 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures - ATR Notes, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Arizona - Colorado), 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - United States: Cross Country Lectures (Illinois - Wisconsin), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - United States: Cross Country 1964 Lectures, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - United States: Cross Country 1967 Lectures, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - United States: Cross Country Post-1967 Lectures, 1969-1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - United States: Lecture Notices, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - United States: Lecture Notices, circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
  - United States: Lecture Notices, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - United States: Local and East Coast Lectures, 1941-1965 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - United States: Local and East Coast Lectures, 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Series V: Political Activities
  Contains correspondence and campaign materials regarding her activities with the ALP from 1940-1960, including her 1949 congressional campaign, and correspondence, position papers, and other material pertaining to the her campaign for Lt. Governor of New York on the Independent Socialist Party ticket in 1958. Rubinstein's long standing relationship with the Robert Louis Stevenson School, including her legal and political struggles, is reflected in correspondence and legal documents, ending with her resignation in 1952. Also included are documents and ephemera from the Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience, several pamphlets Rubinstein wrote or edited for them, and several files of Communist Party ephemera.
  - American Labor Party, 1940-1948 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - American Labor Party, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - American Labor Party, 1951-1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience, 1965-1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience: Community Control of Schools, 1965-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience: Pamphlets, 1968-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Child Care Council, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party: Poland, 1967-1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party: United States, 1959, 1989, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - DuBois, W.E.B.: Rubinstein's Notes for Seminar, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Federal Theatre Project Research Center (at George Mason University), 1979-1994 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Fund for Social Analysis, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Harlem Six, 1966-1982 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Robert Louis Stevenson School: New York State Education Department Correspondence, 1934-1953 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Robert Louis Stevenson School: Rubinstein Correspondence, 1941-1961, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Robert Louis Stevenson School: Rubinstein, Annette T. (Acting as Owner) vs. The United States, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Robert Louis Stevenson School: Senate Hearings (re: Communist Ownership of Schools for War Veterans), 1956 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Rubinstein Electoral Campaigns, 1949, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - United Independent Socialist Committee, 1940-1960 (Box Shared Tamiment 209, Folder 1)
  - United States Senate: Temporary National Economic Committee (Confidential Memorandum from A.A. Berle Jr., with ATR's Notes), 1938 (Box Shared Tamiment 209, Folder 2)
- Series VI: Writings
  About half of this series consists of Rubinstein's book reviews (mostly typescripts, published and unpublished) and her literary and non-literary articles, many of which appeared in Mainstreamor Science and Society. For The Great Tradition in English Literaturethere are typescripts, correspondence, publicity materials and reviews. There is correspondence and contracts pertaining to the publication and distribution of I Vote My Conscience. Later writings include memorial articles and a memoir about her mother, Jean Rubinstein.
  - Articles: Literary (mostly typescripts, published and unpublished) [1 of 2], 1960-1977 (Box Shared Tamiment 209, Folder 3)
  - Articles: Literary (mostly typescripts, published and unpublished) [2 of 2], 1960-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles: Non-Literary, 1958-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews A-C (mostly typescripts, published and unpublished, arranged alphabetically by author), 1957-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book Reviews D-H, 1958-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book Reviews J-L, 1962-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book Reviews M-O, 1958-1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book Reviews P-R, 1956-1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book Reviews S-U, 1957-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Book Reviews V-Z, 1960-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Book Reviews in Newspapers (clippings), 1946-1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Contracts, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Goldway, David: Memorial Article, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Great Tradition in English Literature: Correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Great Tradition in English Literature: Correspondence, 1955-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Great Tradition in English Literature: Publicity, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Great Tradition in English Literature: Typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Humboldt, Charles - Memorial Article, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Marcantonio, Vito: Memorial ( I Vote My Conscience), 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rhodes, Irwin (1911-1990; ATR's brother): Memorial Article (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rubinstein, Jean (1885-1973; ATR's mother): Memoir, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Addendum, 1909-2007
  The first accrual of the series has been arranged alphabetically. Later accessions have not been arranged by an archivist. The unarranged materials can be found in box 4 and 6.
  This series contains materials donated after the initial processing of the collection in 2001. This series mostly contains correspondence, including a significant amount of greeting cards from her family members, friends, and students. The series also contains an unpublished typescript, Annette T. Rubinstein: Author, Educator, Activist(2002), by Gerald Meyer, her passport, and loose materials, mostly related to her work in the Brecht Forum and the publication Science and Society.
  - Annette T. Rubinstein: Author, Educator, Activist(Typescript by Gerald Meyer, 33 pp.), 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Material and Correspondence With Biographer Tina Baker, 1942-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Brecht Forum / New York Marxist School, 1986-2001 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: China, 1987-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: China, 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Europe ("personal letters"), 1955-2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Family, 1909-2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: General, 1950-1994 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: General, 1995-2001 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence General II, 1968, 1992-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Literary and Political, 1942-1989 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Literary and Political, 1991-2001 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Publishers, 1945-1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Researchers, 1946-2001 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Publicity: Classes, Lectures, Political Activity, Testimonials, etc., 1954-2001 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Science and Society, 1986-2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Series VIII: Photographs, 1905-2001 (Box 6)
  This series contains a combination of black-and-white and color photographs, depicting images of Rubinstein from her laters years, at various events, family activities, and during trips to China. The photographs include detailed captions by Rubinstein. The series also includes two cards, a holiday card from Paul Robeson and an invitation to an event honoring Robeson.